So we now turn to the parts of the problem, which is perhaps, let's say, not as glamorous as some
이제 문제의 일부로 넘어가 보죠. 이 부분은 다른 부분만큼 화려하진
of the rest of it, but it is perhaps the most essential, which is finding and crafting your data.
않지만 가장 중요한 부분일 겁니다. 바로 데이터를 찾고 만드는 것이죠.
And there are a bunch of places that people can go to look for data to hunt data.
데이터를 찾고 데이터를 사냥할 수 있는 장소가 많아요
But the first, the first place you go.
하지만 제일 먼저 가는 곳이잖아요
First and foremost, of course, is your own proprietary data that your company has.
가장 중요한 건 귀사의 독점 데이터죠
That is something which hopefully is pertains directly to the problem you're solving, and is going
여러분이 해결하려는 문제와 직접 관련이 있으면 좋겠고 미세한
to be crucial for your fine tuning.
조정에 아주 중요할 거예요
In the case of the pretend fictitious Rag project, we did.
가짜로 만든 랙 프로젝트의 경우 그렇게 했죠
We we pretended we had the shared drive of the company that we used then to build our knowledge base.
우린 우린 지식 기반 구축에 사용한 회사의 공유 드라이브가 있는 척했죠
That's an example of where we went to find proprietary data.
사유 데이터를 찾는 예가 바로 그거죠
In the case of of my business, Nebula, we have information about talent and jobs, careers that we
제 사업인 네뷸라의 경우 독자 모델을 훈련하는 데 쓸 수 있는 재능과 직업,
can use to train proprietary Models.
경력에 대한 정보가 있어요
So finding your own company, proprietary data sets that are specific for your problem, that's the
여러분의 문제에 구체적인 소유 데이터 세트를 찾는 것이 첫 번째
first place to start.
시작이죠
Of course, then there is Kaggle, a wonderful resource for data scientists.
캐글도 있습니다 데이터 과학자를 위한 훌륭한 자원이죠
You probably heard of it and used it.
아마 들어보고 사용하셨겠죠
If not, go and take a look at it.
없으면 가서 봐요
It's got, uh, so much, uh, data.
데이터가 정말 많아요
Data, um, that goes over a long period of time that people have contributed to Kaggle.
데이터는 오랜 기간 동안 사람들이 캐글에 기여한 거예요
And then there is, of course, hugging face.
그리고 포옹하는 얼굴도 있죠
Uh, that is just such a fabulous resource for us.
저희에겐 정말 멋진 자원이에요
And we will be using hugging Face in just a moment.
포옹하는 표정도 잠시 후에 보여드릴게요
There's also synthetic data, as it happens.
합성 데이터도 있어요
For our Rag project, we didn't use a real company's shared drive.
우리 랙 프로젝트는 진짜 회사의 공유 드라이브를 사용하지 않았어요
We used an LLM to generate synthetic data and that is an option.
LLM을 이용해 합성 데이터를 생성했는데 그건 옵션이죠
There are pros and cons, of course.
물론 장단점이 있죠
If you're if you're trying to use the frontier model to actually, uh, learn from the data, then it
프런티어 모델을 사용해 데이터를 얻으려 한다면 프런티어 모델이 데이터를 생성하고 학습하는
may not make sense to have the frontier model generate the data and then learn from it, but if you're
것은 말이 안 될 수도 있습니다 하지만 자신만의 모델을 만들거나 더
trying to build your own model, or you're trying to build a cheaper model, that's that's going to
저렴한 모델을 만들려 한다면 프런티어 모델이 시드를 하게
be seeded by a frontier model, then you could use the front end model to generate some some data and
될 것입니다 프런트엔드 모델을 이용해 데이터를 생성하고 그 데이터를 더 작고 저렴하고
then use that data to train your smaller, cheaper, more lightweight model.
가벼운 모델을 훈련하는 데 사용할 수 있죠
So the various circumstances where synthetic data makes sense.
다양한 상황에서 합성 데이터가 말이 되죠
And then I'll mention that there are specialist companies whose task it is to go out there and curate
그런 다음 여러분을 위해 데이터 세트를 큐레이팅하는 작업을 하는 전문 회사들이 있다고
a data set for you.
말씀드리죠
We actually encountered this company earlier when we were looking at one of the leaderboards, the leaderboard
이 회사를 만난 적이 있어요 예전에 실이라는 이름의 leaderboard를
called seal, which were business specific leaderboards for Llms that is put together by a company called
볼 때였죠 Scale이라는 회사에서 만든 Lms의 비즈니스용 leaderboard예요
And scale specializes in building crafted data sets for your problem.
비율은 여러분의 문제를 위해 정교한 데이터 세트를 만드는 데 전문이죠
So that is another place to go.
또 다른 장소죠
In our case though, we are going to Hugging Face, which is a treasure trove of data and it contains
하지만 우리는 얼굴 안기 게임을 할 거예요 아주 귀중한 데이터고 공동체가 기여한 데이터가
much data contributed by the community, including this particular data set.
많이 들어 있어요 이 특정 데이터 세트도 포함해서요
Scrape over many years of Amazon reviews.
수년에 걸친 아마존 리뷰를 긁어모아요
That is, uh, enormous.
정말 거대하네요
It is an absolutely enormous data set.
정말 방대한 데이터 세트예요
And in addition to the reviews that it takes, it also has metadata just associated with the products,
리뷰를 작성하는 것 외에도 제품과 관련된 메타데이터도 있어요
including the description of the products and their prices.
제품 설명과 가격을 포함해서요
And that, of course, is exactly what we're after, product descriptions and prices.
그게 바로 우리가 원하는 거죠 제품 설명과 가격이요
And this data set has them in large quantities.
이 데이터 세트에는 그 양이 아주 많아요
And so it is perfect for us.
그래서 저희에게 완벽하죠
This is where we will be heading.
우리가 향할 곳은 여기예요
So how do you go about digging into the data.
데이터를 어떻게 파헤칠 건가요?
What are the steps that you take?
어떤 단계를 밟나요?
We're going to be doing some of this work today, and we're going to be refining some of it tomorrow.
오늘 이 작업 중 일부를 하고 일부는 내일 다듬을 거예요
Um, but there are these six different stages, perhaps, to getting deep into the data.
데이터를 깊이 파고들려면 6단계가 있어요
First of all, there's a time when you're Investigating, just understanding the data, what fields
먼저, 조사할 때 데이터를 이해하는 시기가 있어요 어떤 필드를 가질까요?
to have?
데이터가 얼마나 꽉 찼나요?
What kind of data quality issues do you have?
데이터 품질에 어떤 문제가 있나요?
Then typically at least the way I like to approach this is then parsing in that data into a structure
일반적으로 제가 접근하는 방법은 데이터를 구조로 파싱 하는 겁니다 그럼
which is going to be easier to handle.
처리하기 더 쉬워지죠
Um, that, that's, that's uh, so that you're no longer working with raw data sets.
더는 가공되지 않은 데이터로 작업하지 않아도 되죠
You're working typically with, with objects at that point.
그 시점에서 일반적으로 개체로 작업하죠
It's great then to do some visualizations, it's important to see things like the, the how wide, how
시각화를 하는 건 좋은 일입니다 얼마나 넓고 얼마나 퍼져 있는지 보는 건 중요하죠
Some of your values are when we're thinking of things like prices of products, what's the range in
제품 가격 같은 걸 생각할 때 가격의 차이는 어느 정도인가요?
Does it turn out that there are a lot of that the distribution is skewed in some way.
분포가 어떤 식으로든 삐뚤어져 있는 게 많은가요?
So visualize it so you can get a really good sense of it.
상상해 보세요 그럼 감이 잘 오겠죠 get it get it
Now a deeper assessment of data quality.
이제 데이터 품질을 더 심도 있게 평가해 보죠
Understand what kind of limitations you have with your data.
데이터의 한계를 이해해야 해요
Um, that will help you decide how to take action on it and curate is when you then go and decide how
이를 통해 어떻게 행동하고 큐레이팅할지 결정하고 이 데이터 세트를 어떻게
you're going to craft this data set.
만들지 결정하게 되죠
For example, if it turns out that you discover that a quarter of your data is in has poor data quality
예를 들어 데이터의 4분의 1이 데이터 품질이 나쁘다는 사실이 밝혀진다면 해당 데이터를
in some way, you may decide just to exclude that data altogether.
아예 제외하기로 할 수도 있죠
You may think that you have a big enough sample that you can focus on the three quarters.
샘플이 충분히 있어서 4분의 3에 집중할 수 있다고 생각할 수도 있어요
If you find that your data set is very imbalanced in some way, and you're concerned that that as part
데이터 집합이 어떤 면에서 매우 불균형하고 훈련의 일부로서
of training, the model will only learn a sort of a particular balance of the data, then this would
모델이 데이터의 특정 균형만 배울까 봐 걱정된다면 이 시기가 잠재적으로
be a time to potentially fix address that balance.
그 균형을 바로잡을 때죠
So curating is about crafting the data set that is most suitable for your training and then saving it.
큐레이팅은 훈련에 가장 적합한 데이터 세트를 만들어 저장하는 거예요
In our case, we'll be uploading it to the Huggingface hub.
어깅페이스 허브에 업로드할 거예요
That's the final step before you'd be ready for training.
훈련하기 전 마지막 단계죠
So with that, we're going to head to JupyterLab for the first time with our new project, and we're
이제 새로운 프로젝트를 가지고 처음으로 JupyterLab으로 가서 데이터를
going to get about curating some data.
큐레이팅하는 법을 배워볼 거예요. HET
See you there.
거기서 봐요